Custer mss., 1876-1933 LMC 1245
Lilly Library
Custer mss.
1876-1933
Lilly Library
Various
LMC 1245
1 Box 1 standard
The Custer mss., 1876-1933, consists of a copy of the Proceedings of the Court of Inquiry, January 13, 1879, in the case of Major Marcus A. Reno concerning his conduct at the Battle of the Little Big Horn River, 1876.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 1967
Biographical Note
Major Marcus A. Reno, 1835-1889, was a soldier involved in the Battle of the Little Big Horn River in 1876. Reno was born in Carollton, Illinois. After the death of his mother in 1848, Reno applied for the United States Military Academy at West Point. He graduated in 1857 and was assigned to the 1st U.S. Dragoons. During the Civil War, he fought for the Union Army at the battles of Antietam, Kelly's Ford, Williamsport, and Cold Harbor, among others. By 1876 Reno was serving as the senior officer under General George Armstrong Custer, 1839-1876. At the Battle of Little Bighorn, Reno led his company to retreat to a defensive position while Custer's company was overrun. His unit was the only unit to survive the battle. A court of inquiry on January 13, 1879 cleared Reno of charges of cowardice, but his behavior during the battle continued to be portrayed as the antithesis to Custer's brave "last stand." Reno was court marshalled on unrelated charges in 1880, but this ruling was overturned posthumously in 1967. He was then reinterred at Custer National Cemetery.
Scope and Contents Note
The Custer mss., 1876-1933, consists of a copy of the Proceedings of the Court of Inquiry, January 13, 1879, in the case of Major Marcus A. Reno concerning his conduct at the Battle of the Little Big Horn River, 1876; stenographic report of the testimony, 1879, edited by William James Ghent; penciled notes on the case probably by Walter Mason Camp; photostats of letters by William T. Sherman, August 5, 1876; Marcus A. Reno, July 15,1876; and a photostat of the petition of enlisted survivors of the Battle of the Little Big Horn, July 4, 1876, to the President and the Representatives of the United States; and photographs of the Custer battleground area. A list of the photographs (over 400, mostly from the 1920s, pertaining to Custer and the Battle of Little Big Horn) is in the box of pictures.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged following original order.
Americana; West (U.S.); Little Bighorn, Battle of the, Mont., 1876.; Little Bighorn Battlefield (Mont.); Trials (Military offenses); Reno, Marcus A. (Marcus Albert), 1835-1889; Custer, George A. (George Armstrong), 1839-1876.; Sherman, William T. (William Tecumseh), 1820-1891
- Brinninstool, E.A. Camp of an old Sioux woman near Crawford, Nebraska, 1926; 3 photographs
- Brinninstool, E.A. Cemetery at Fort Robinson, Nebraska. Baptiste Carmer and Moses Milner, 1926; 4 photographs
- Brinninstool, E.A. Cook's ranch and family, 1926; 14 photographs
- Brinninstool, E.A. 50th anniversary Custer celebration at Crow Agency, 1926; 69 photographs
- Brinninstool, E.A. Crave of John "Portugee" Phillips at Cheyenne, 1926; 4 photographs
- Deming, Edwin Willard. Battle of the Little Big Horn, n.d.
  Scope and Contents
  Photograph by DeWitt Ward of a painting by Deming, accompanied by commentary on the painting by Robert Spurrier Ellison
- Eber, Ells. Custer's Last Fight, n.d.
  Photograph by E.A. Brinninstool of painting located in Dresden, Germany, museum. Accompanied by negative, filed separately.
- Eder, Martha L. Warrior teepee at Pitchfork canyon, 1928; 1 Photograph
- Edwards, Elsa Spear. Crow Indian campground and site of Wagon Box site, 1926; 7 photographs
- Ellison, Robert Spurrier. Custer Hill, Little Big Horn, Reno Hill, Rosebud River; and friends at the unveiling of Charley Reynolds' monument, 1938; 12 photographs 2 attributed to Mrs. Marsh and Monte Robinson
- Finney, W.R. Crow agency, 1926; 4 photographs without negatives
- Garber, Mrs. 50th anniversary of Custer fight, incl. 1 photo of actor Bill Hart, 1926; 9 photographs
- Re: Hooker: William Francis., 4 photographs
  Nos. 2-4 are as an older man, positioned against a brick wall
  - 1) By Klein, Milwaukee, 1905-1906
  - 2) By Ewing Calloway, N.Y., n.d.
  - 3) By Ewing Calloway?, n.d.
  - 4) By Ewing Galloway?, n.d.
- Huffman, L.A. Custer's Hill and related scenes, of 1877-1926, n.d.
  Set of prints, Nos. 1-15, with copyright notice
- Johnson, Jessamine Spear. 50th anniversary of Custer's fight and ceremonies at the grave of the unknown trooper, with Sioux, Crow, and Cheyenne people, 1926; 30 photographs
  With letter of J.S. Johnson to Miss Murphy, 1927, July 17
- Johnson, Jessamine Spear. Rosebud Ranch, Mrs. Johnson, Crow Agency, and Buffalo Bill Museum, n.d., 7 photographs
- Kopac, Emil. Reno Hill, and Kopac ranch in Nebraska, 1928; 9 photographs
- Krieg, Mr. 50th anniversary of Custer's fight and ceremonies at the grave of the unknown trooper, 1926; 35 photographs
  With letter of George G. Osten to R.S. Ellison, 1927, Apr. 30
- Kuhlman, Edith and Robert. Custer Battle site, 1935-1936; 24 photographs
- Mahaffey, Edna M. Prospecting on the Medicine Bow, By Bear Tracks for Standing Elk, n.d.
  Original pencil sketch; on verso: Standing Elks Lament, 4 lines in ink
- Murphy, Claire H. Crow Agency, 1926; 9 photographs
  No. 9 is Bill Hart, actor
- Murphy, Claire H. President Coolidge's summer home in the Black Hills, 1927; 2 photographs
  Photo of C.H. Murphy. 1927?
- Pray, Judge. 50th anniversary of Custer's fight and ceremonies for the unknown trooper, 1927; 7 photographs
- Rose, H.N. General Custer at camp at Ft. Hayes, Kansas and at Ft. Lincoln, Dakota Territory during 1869-1874, n.d., 4 photographs
  Prints from the collection of H.N. Rose, photographer of San Antonio, Texas, 1934.
- Scott, D.C. 50th anniversary, Custer Battle, 1926; 34 photographs
  Nos. 4 and 5 are Bill Hart, actor
- Teakell, A.M. "Comanche," survivor of Custer Massacre, n.d., 1926
  1 photo, copyrighted; with photo of Independence Rock, unidentified photo, and clipping in envelope from A.J. Hazlett, 1926, July 3
- Thompson, H.H. Crows building a Sweat Teepee, 1926; 1 Photograph
- Thompson, H.H. George Grier, Dr. Grenwell, W.M. Camp, 1908; 1 Photograph
- Vickery, H.F. 50th anniversary of Custer Fight, 1926; 22 photographs
- Wildschut, W. "Sham battle" on 40th anniversary of Custer's defeat, 1916; 10 photographs
  With note by Claire H. Murphy from envelope of 1927, July 21
- Yates, G.L. 50th anniversary of Custer Fight, 1926; 32 photographs
- [?] Veterans' photos by a friend of Claire H. Murphy, n.d., 4 photographs
- Miscellaneous: White Bull, Sioux Chief
  Probably an enlargement of one of the Indian photos taken during the 50th anniversary ceremonies
- Miscellaneous: materials
  - 1) Photo of home of Dr. McLoughlin, Oregon City, Ore, 1946
    With address of Mrs. J.L. Schober on verso
  - 2) Postcard featuring the battle site, General Custer and Curley, Native American scout, n.d.
  - 3) Souvenir folder of Custer battlefield commemorating the anniversary of the Battle of Little Bighorn, n.d.
  - 4) Souvenir Folder of Sheridan, Wyoming, n.d.
  - 5) Photograph of drawing of Fort Phil Kearney (no artist, no photographer, no dates)